[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software you already know that Android
and iOS are operating systems designed
to run applications well algorand is
also an operating system just one
designed to run run decentralized
applications enabling true peer-to-peer
programmable value
exchanges Android and iOS operating
systems algorand decentralized operating
system blockchain doesn't sound so scary
now does it especially not scary you can
build on algorand in Python the same
pure semantically normal python you
learned back in school and know fluently
no gimmicks try it today head to algo
kit. that's ALG o kit t. to set up your
environment and get coding in just 5
minutes welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Gregory cap Hammer
today's guest is hyam Wright hyam is a
senior staff software engineer at Google
he is the technical lead for the C++
concurrency Primitives that they use at
Google along with with teaching at
Carnegie meling University ham was an
editor of and contributor to the book
called software engineering at Google
that book is the topic of today's show
Welcome to software engineering radio
hyam thanks Greg it's great to be here
thanks for taking your time to
participate in the show today in order
to dive in I want to read you a few
quotes that come from the software
engineering at Google book and if you
would be so kind to do so I'm going to
read the quote and I would love it if
you could contextualize it and then try
to explain it does that sound cool
sounds great all right the quote number
one is as follows with a sufficient
number of users of an API it does not
matter what you promise in the contract
all observable behaviors of your system
will be depended on by somebody so this
is probably the thing that gets quoted
the most and it's come to be known as
Ham's law and I should be quick to point
out that I did not name it Ham's law so
I I want to be humble in that respect
but this is an observation that came
from many years of doing software
maintenance activities across the Google
code base and recognizing that every
time we tried to change something as
simple as a line number or a comment in
a file or a log message tests would fail
in various interesting ways and we
started to realize that if we get enough
users of our system anything we try to
change will break somebody in some way
this isn't a new observation there's an
XKCD comic about it there's other places
you can find references to this online
but the presentation in the quote that
you mentioned and the name hams law came
out of the book so I heard you say that
sometimes you could make a very simple
change and then a test case would fail
can you give us like a concrete example
of when you've had that type of
experience at Google sure so we were
trying to reorganize one of Google's
core file API Primitives and the result
was that we were moving functions in
different header files we were changing
just the basic structure of these
Primitives to be more understandable and
be more consistent across our code base
what ended up happening was that at one
point we changed a comment line which
ended up changing line numbers within a
file we didn't think anything of it but
we run all the tests just to make sure
we're not breaking anything and tests
started to fail it turns out that some
test somewhere was including the line
number of the log message in their
validation in the test now this is not
good practice you should never depend on
things like line numbers that you don't
have any control over but somebody had
copied the error message and pasted it
verbatim into their test and so when we
changed the comment it reflowed the file
changed the line number and the test
started to fail so even the line number
of a error message was an observable
behavior that somebody was depending on
all right thanks for those insights
we're going to talk more about testing
later in the show but now I want to turn
to quotation number two so here it is
traditional managers worry about how to
get things done whereas great managers
worry about what things get done and
trust their team to figure out how to do
it what does that one mean Hyrum this is
really about trusting as the quote says
the people that work for you to do the
job in the way that they think best as a
manager you may manage many different
teams and many different individuals and
you cannot be the domain expert in all
of the things that you are responsible
for it can be temp especially if you
have a technical background and Lead
technical teams to jump in and dictate
exactly how they should solve the
problem that you're giving them but if
you're smart and as the quote mentions
great managers will just tell the team
what needs to be done and let them as
the domain experts figure out how to
accomplish it maner still needs to
support the team that doesn't mean
you're completely hands-off but it also
means that you trust them and their
expertise to get the job done okay so
those two quote ations have revealed
very clearly that the book has both
Technical and professional content
inside of it this leads me to the next
question when you were writing the book
what type of audience did you have in
mind so we really want to share the
things that we had learned within Google
with other practitioners my other
co-editors and I spent a lot of time
talking at conferences and other
external fora about the experiences that
we have at Google and we found that we
kept saying the same things over and
over again we wanted to be able to write
down the lessons that we had learned in
a way that made sense for this external
audience we also found out that there
was a significant desire within Academia
to take some of these lessons and
present them in college courses and so
every once in a while I'll find some
random College course somewhere that
lists the book as either a required
reading or supplementary material for
their course and that really makes me
happy because it means that this message
is getting to a much broader audience
than we even intended when we started
writing so if you won't mind me saying
it actually turns out to be the case
that I teach one of those random
software engineering courses and we use
the software engineering book in the
class well I'm grateful to hear it I
hope that your students find it useful
yeah we find it really useful and one of
the things I noticed in the book is that
even though it's called software
engineering at Google the entire book
isn't about topics like testing or
debugging or writing computer programs
so why did you decide to have a book
that has both technical content and
additional content about things like
knowledge sharing or project management
software engineering encompasses a much
broader scope than just programming I
tend to think of programming as
carpentry somebody can be a very good
Carpenter and they can do very excellent
work but that's not sufficient to build
a house you need Architects you need
concrete workers you need a bunch of
other trades and skilled individuals to
build the house you need somebody that's
overseeing the entire project and so
software engineering in some sense
really encompasses the entire process
required to construct a software program
or a software system rather and not just
programming both people that get hired
into a place like Google as well as
people that you know are in in
University they think my job is to write
software I'm not successful unless I've
written some code today but our job is
actually to solve problems and there's a
lot of pieces to the problem solving
process that are Beyond just writing
code thanks for your response I think
that brings up a good point can you give
a concrete example of how software
engineering is different than
programming at Google so if your job is
just a program then you'll spend your
time optimizing for how much code can I
write today and you may actually write
more code than you need to software
engineering is an interesting field in
that if you're writing the same thing
that you wrote yesterday you're probably
doing it wrong software can be reused we
have libraries we have all kinds of
abstractions that we can build you
really shouldn't even though we teach
undergrads how to write link lists if
anyone writes a link list in a
professional setting they're probably
doing it wrong and those kinds of things
I think really differentiate why
software engineering as a whole if we're
not careful we can confuse it with
programming and we can optimize for
programming and we really need to be
thinking about the whole system and the
whole software engineering process when
I was reading the book one of the things
I noticed is that when you're working at
Google scale and efficiency challenges
are a really big deal and so you
mentioned reuse a moment ago but can you
comment briefly what are some of the
challenges you faced as a software
engineer at Google when it comes to
things related to scale or efficiency
challenges so I've often said the
problems at Google are not problems of
kind email existed before Gmail but no
one had given a gigabyte at the time of
data storage right that's a scale
problem search engines had existed
before Google but no one had given the
comprehensiveness that the Google search
engine did when we came out right so
like they're problems of scale not of
kind in software engineering some of our
problems exist about testing how do we
test everything that needs to be tested
in a reasonable way how do we index all
of our source code and give
discoverability into our process in a
reasonable way how do we ensure that we
have that we have appropriate quality
across our codebase in a reasonable way
right when I say in a reasonable way
we're talking about codebase that's
hundreds of millions of lines large
that's not anything anyone can review
manually when we do migration how can we
do that in a a reasonable way in a
scalable way we're really looking for
sublinear scaling costs as opposed to
something that scales with the side of
the size of the codebase because as the
codebase continues to grow you don't
want to have to be investing ever more
resources into just keeping it
maintained you mentioned several
concrete examples like for example being
able to index all of the source code can
you explain why you would need to do
that indexing and what would be the
Practical ramification of getting the
indexing wrong so that it didn't handle
the scale that was necessary so there's
a couple of consumers of something like
a codebase index one is as I mentioned
the large scale maintenance tools that
read this index and then can run stack
analysis and other kinds of tools across
the codebase to do either maintenance
activities or find bugs or other kinds
of analyses that give insights into the
software for the owners of of every
project at Google another consumer is
Engineers themselves right they want to
look at the code browser they want to
see what's going on
we find that a great way of learning to
write software is looking at other
people's software and finding out what
they did so if you're using a new API
for the first time you can browse
Google's internal codebase and see how
is that API being used and what way
should I be using that API if we're not
indexing everything then those two
processes fall down we can't effectively
migrate everything because we can't get
a complete picture of the world and
somebody may not be able to find the
examples that they need in their
existing
or to make the changes that they need to
to their existing system so when you
talked about indexing it sounds like
that's a challenge you've faced in the
past I'm wondering since the book was
published have there been any new scale
or efficiency challenges You' faced I
think one of them that's not just us but
the entire industry we're looking at how
can we use our physical plant more
efficiently how can we use the systems
that we have how can we run our software
more efficiently so that we can better
provide service to customers provide
service to more customers you know AI
has become a set of workloads that
requires a significant amount of compute
power in the last few years and we're
thinking about how can we make sure that
we provide those services to users in a
scalable way without having to
completely rebuild our physical plant
and so these software engineering
scalability problems still have a lot of
meaning today when you talked about the
idea of indexing the code you also
mentioned the phrase you need to read
the code so I'm wondering can you talk a
little bit about some of the strategies
that you employ at Google when it comes
to for example working in a team or
sharing knowledge effectively we think
about code as something that is written
once but it's read many times and so we
actually optimize for readability not
writability and what this means is that
style guides and other
tooling essentially encourage maybe a
little bit more verbosity in the
codebase which may take more time to
write but also means that somebody
coming along later will be able to read
and understand that code easier that's a
really good point later in the show I
hope to talk about style guides before
we get into the details about style
guides I wanted to point out a couple
really catchy phrases that I remember
reading in the book so this first phrase
was called the Genius myth what is the
genius myth at Google so I love that
phrase that's from one of the chapters
written by Brian Fitzpatrick who I've
known for many years and it's basically
this idea that in Tech generally we
think about the genius programmer the
person that can do everything and we
sometimes hold up examples like lonus
tals or Guido van rossom or Bill Gates
or somebody that you know is really a
standout in their field and that's
actually not true I'm not trying to say
that those folks aren't really smart in
in in their domains but if you look at
how systems are actually built they're
not built by just one person in their
space
you know building a thing and it kind of
springing fully formed from the mind of
Zeus they're built over many iterations
with many different inputs with many
different people involved and over time
that number of people involved in that
team will be better than any specific
single
individual so at Google if there is a
genius myth how do you organize your
teams in order to ensure that you don't
fall trapped to the genius myth we want
to ensure a lot of communication within
the team that may be by email or chat or
through code review We want to make sure
that things are done in as public a way
as possible now there's business
constraints around how broadly you can
share something within or without a
company but we want to make sure that
things are being done as publicly as
possible that means getting early
feedback on things like design docs or
project design uh code review means
getting being willing to be receptive to
feedback a lot of Engineers myself
included a lot of early career Engineers
specifically con struggle with getting
concrete and sometimes critical feedback
on their code or their designs it's not
that you're a bad person it's that how
can we help you improve your system and
the reaction to that is oftentimes we
tend to hide things we tend to keep it
hidden until we think that we have the
best product but over time that actually
takes longer to get to the best outcome
and it doesn't always lead to the best
outcome because you can't fix things
farther down the road yeah a moment ago
you used the word hiding and in fact
that connects to another quotation I
remember in the book The quotation was
something like hiding considered harmful
can you tell us why it's harmful to hide
based on what you said a moment ago so
it relates to a lot of those things I
just mentioned we want to get early
feedback on designs and implementation
we know that the team is stronger than
any individual and so getting good
feedback on a design in process will
give you a better outcome if you hide it
for too long then you might actually get
to the point where you can't actually
make meaningful changes based upon
feedback because certain parts of the
process have already finished and you
can't go back and remake some of those
decisions so it sounds like you're
saying if software Engineers are going
to hide their work it may limit their
productivity and also limit the
productivity of their team exact so my
next question is at Google how do you
actually measure engineering
productivity what strategies have you
developed so I wish that I could say
here is a recipe that everyone can use
and we can you know apply engineering
productivity to your organization if you
just do what we did I will take a step
back and say the entire book was not
written as a you should do what we do it
was written as a these are the problems
that we have encountered and these are
the ways that we have solved them
hopefully as useful to your organization
so as I talk about things keep kind of
keep that in mind so engineering
productivity is a really difficult thing
to measure there's a lot of concrete
things we can measure you can measure
line of code written or number of bugs
fixed there's a famous Dilbert comic
where one of the people says I'm going
to go code myself a minivan this weekend
after the boss says that he's going to
reward the number of bugs that people
fix so you can have bad metrics the way
that we approach engineering
productivity is first of all we talked
to engineering leaders what do you want
to measure what are you trying to
improve what outcomes do you expect and
frankly would you change your behavior
if you get an out come different than
the one you expect we often times Find
engineering leaders are interested in
knowing something but finding it out
isn't actually going to change their
behavior and so there takes a lot of
honest discussion to make sure that
we're measuring things that are
meaningfully going to change the
behavior of the organization and then we
talk about goals and signals and metrics
you know a goal is something that you
the outcome that you want it may not be
necessarily clearly specified but it's
the outcome that you want a signal is
the thing that you would like to measure
but often times it's difficult to
measure the signal concretely you know
if I ask you is your happiness better
today than it was yesterday like you
might be able to say specific events
happened that increased your happiness
but that's sometimes a difficult thing
to actually concretely measure metrics
are the concrete proxies for signals
that we can actually measure we have to
be careful in designing our metrics
because we want to make sure that they
are the things that actually properly
reflect the signals that will give us
the goal that we
want
everybody most people will game metrics
if we tell them that this is what
they're being measured by they will
start performing to the metric and so we
want to make pretty certain that the
metric is the thing we care about the
other side and this kind of goes against
what I was just talking about in hiding
is that sometimes we will tell people we
are measuring something but we don't
tell them exactly how like that it will
be used or that can be used we don't
want them to change their behavior based
upon the fact that we're doing measuring
we want to change their behavior maybe
in some other way but we don't want them
to just increase the number of changes
that they make or the number of bugs
that they fix because we happen to be
measuring that thing as part of a more
holistic hole Yeah you made a couple
really interesting comments which is
when we're presented with a metric we
sometimes over optimize towards that
metric another thing I heard you say a
moment ago is that sometimes engineering
managers will want to measure something
but then actually not change their
behavior when they get that data can you
comment why does that happen hyam I'm
not exactly sure all the time I think
sometimes it comes down to we have a
natural human reaction to want to hear
the things that we want to hear right
there's a certain confirmation bias in
people and we're looking for specific
outcomes Google is a data driven company
but like many datadriven organizations
there is a temptation to find the data
that matches your existing worldview and
so if that's going to be the case then
it doesn't really make sense to try to
measure productivity in a different way
now I would say this is pretty rare most
of the time when people are looking for
an engineering productivity experience
they're trying to find something that
will actively help their organization
and they're willing to adjust based up
the things they find I know you were one
of the leaders of Google's code health
Team first very quickly could you define
what the code Health team was and then
perhaps could you share a con example of
how you measured productivity on that
team so our team was responsible for
building out a platform that basically
managed all of the large scale change
automation that flowed into Google's
codebase now there's a lot of words
there and I don't know how do we'll get
into some of the large scale change
stuff I think a little bit later but
that team basically provided service to
other teams to ensure that they were
able to make effective broad sweeping
changes across go Google's entire code
base one of the ways that we measured
productivity was not necessarily in how
our specific team performed because
ultimately we're serving other parts of
the company we're looking at things like
are we able to effectively provide
service to those other teams how easy is
it for them to onboard into the platform
how easy is it for them to integrate
with the platform if they're already on
or if they're adding new changes into
the system what is simple things like
throughput and latency of changes that
are flowing through our platform
ultimately our platform was responsible
for making Engineers across Google more
effective and more productive and so
those metrics helped us know if we were
doing our job thanks for that response
if listeners are interested in learning
more about measuring engineering
productivity they might want to check
out a prior episode of software
engineering radio which was number 317
we'll reference that in the show notes
for greater details ham what I'd like to
do now is turn our attention to
something you mentioned previously which
was the idea of style guides and code
reviews I know you're an expert in C++
programming could you give an example of
a style guide that Google adopted in the
context of C++ well first I'd say I'm
not sure anyone can be an expert in C++
it's a very complex language and
ecosystem but I appreciate the comment
our C++ style guide is actually
published it's publicly available you
can search for it and find out some of
the rules and requirements that we have
we have a number of rules I mentioned
earlier that are optimized more for the
reader and not necessarily for the
writer things like don't use Auto all
the time you know when Auto was first
the auto keyword was first released as a
type of type deduction in C++ 11 there
were a lot of C++ commentators that said
always use Auto use it every place you
can it helps the compiler it helps you
know the ecosystem or or what have you
we have found that having types spelled
out where reasonable is actually an
important part of program
comprehensibility it means that the
reader of a piece of software doesn't
have to go figure out what this Auto
stands for it may take a little bit more
typing and a little more time but it
actually makes it easier for a reader to
come through now like most sty guide
rules there are reasonable places to use
Auto it's not a pure ban on the auto
keyword but it is a place where we think
you have nuance and use good judgment
instead of just always use it everywhere
so do you have a specific strategy at
Google for enforcing the adherence to
these style guides we have a number of
tools so we have a number of static
analysis tools and linters and other
kinds of pipelines we've found that
style guides are most easily complied
with when Engineers are helped with them
so for example historically style guides
have had a lot of content around
formatting you know you have to use tabs
or spaces or indent this way or you know
braces go on this line or am I using k&r
style or some other style right like
those are actually uninteresting
questions just pick a style and use it
but it also means that we want to be
able to enforce that programmatically so
we can check and see is your code
compliant with Google's you know
whitespace guidelines but also give you
tools to enforce those so for example
cling format which was written at Google
as part of a large scale change process
that will run automatically over code
and just style it the right way as an
engineer I no longer have to remember
where does the brace go or what does the
wi space have to look like because the
tooling enforces it for me and that's
really powerful so are there examples of
things in your style guides that you
can't automatically enforce with a tool
the auto example is one of them right
because it requires a little bit of
nuance there's a number of other pieces
it's been a while since I've been in the
style guide so I don't have any off the
top of my head sadly but there's a
number of other things that require a
little bit of nuance you know should I
name this function this way what does
the comment look like maybe those are
some good examples so when I'm
contributing myself to an open source
project often times these linters or
other Checkers are run in continuous
integration another thing that I often
run in continuous integration is the
test Suite so what I want to do now is
turn our attention to some of the
testing techniques that you've explored
at Google I have to say you wrote a
really interesting talk for the C++
conference and I think it had a tongue
and cheek title the title was all your
tests are terrible Tales From The
Trenches can you tell us a little bit
what was that talk about so that's
actually a talk that I co-ave with Titus
Winters who was another editor on the
software engineering at Google book and
honestly that was the most fun talk to
give and I think that it has really
stood the test of time over the last 10
years you know as we do a lot of changes
to the Google code base we get to see a
lot of tests we run a lot of tests and
we fix a lot of tests and we noticed a
bunch of anti-patterns in testing that
we kind of boiled down and distilled
into this talk I'll let your listeners
go and find the talk themselves it's
it's on YouTube you can find it but
there were patterns things like you know
having too much boilerplate not testing
the right things right if your system
uses a vector for instance like don't
test the behavior of vector which may
change this goes back to Ham's law test
the behavior of your system you know
making sure that your tests are readable
and understandable to users to other
people that may come back come back
through all these were kind of common
principles that we found as part of our
experience in digging through everyone
else's tests across the code base so
later we're going to talk about an
example of what might be a quote unquote
good test case but before we do that I
Remember You Ed the word boilerplate and
that connects to Something in the book
which was about writing the quote
unquote smallest possible test can you
comment briefly what is the quote
unquote smallest possible test for some
source code component you want to test
the basic Behavior lots of tests will
want to test all the corner cases and
every everything and that's useful but
sometimes you actually find that in a
single test case we're going to test a
bunch of different scenarios in a single
test case start by writing the test for
the common scenario then write separate
tests for the borderline conditions the
cases that you expect to fail or expect
to have odd behavior one of the
interesting things about tests is that
they the first user of your system in
many cases and there a great opportunity
to test the apis to experience what a
user of your system will use writing the
simplest possible tests gives you a good
feeling for how a user is going to use
your system in the common case you're
making a really good point I often think
of test cases as being like executable
documentation one of the things I heard
you mention is that when you make the
test small and focused it helps you to
avoid some of the gchas with testing I'm
predicting that one of those gas is
flaky test cases in fact the book says
that flaky test cases are expensive at
Google so this leads me to my next
question what is a flaky test and why
are they expensive at Google so a flaky
test is a test that behaves differently
or appears to behave differently under
the same set of conditions so if I run
the test it may pass and then I run the
test again and it fails I have haven't
changed anything about the system under
test and I haven't changed the test
itself but I'm getting different
outcomes now something has changed in
some way unless there's a you know
Randomness inherent to the test
something has changed but it's often not
considered part of the thing being
tested the reason why they're expensive
there's a couple of reasons one is that
we tend to rerun flaky tests multiple
times in order to actually determine if
they're flaky or not this has obvious
expense in terms of computation cost the
other one is that often times the people
running your tests aren't on your team
so if tests are a way for other people
to validate whether their changes
interact correctly with your software
and you have flaky tests and they run
them and they fail then they have to
spend a bunch of time learning about
your system understanding how or why
this test is flaky and trying to figure
out whether that failure is actually
related to the thing they have changed
or whether it's just a part of the FL of
your system and because of the scale of
tests at Google even if we have tests
that are
flaky 10,000th of the time we're running
enough tests that those will show up
with high degree of probability across a
codebase wide test run it sounds like
you're saying that flaky tests are
expensive for two distinct reasons
number one they have a computational
cost and then number two there's a human
cost associated with figuring out why
the flaky test is failing and then
deciding what you're going to do so this
leads me to my next question how does
Google handle flaky test cases well on a
technical level we rerun the flaky tests
multiple times during off peak hours to
try to determine whether they're flaky
or not and the degree to which they are
flaky our technical ability has
increased a lot over the last several
years and so even when we run all the
tests The Continuous integration system
will determine should I run these flaky
tests or not are they likely to give
good signal as to the correctness of the
change that I have under test and then
it will surface that signal to the
person that's requesting the testing so
that they can make a decision whether
this test is something that they should
look at or not there's two other testing
topics that I wanted to quickly talk
about the book mentions that software
engineers at Google measure the adequacy
of their test Suite through something
called test code coverage what is code
coverage and how do you use it at Google
so code coverage is again a thing that
if you're careful you make the metric
the goal and code coverage is a tool but
it's not the end all of testing it's a
way that we can determine whether a
specific code path is exercised under
tests so if I have a bunch of if
statements in my function that I'm
testing my tests only hit the true
condition on all those statements I'm
really not testing the full
functionality of that function I'm only
testing a specific path and so code
coverage is a way of determining which
paths through a function are being run
while the system is under test
there's a couple of other techniques
that we use as well we use mutation
testing where the system will not
entirely randomly but it will change
lines of code and then rerun the tests
and say wait a minute with this kind of
mutation we would expect a failure in
your test Suite but your test Suite
didn't fail this likely indicates that
you don't have sufficient coverage over
this part of your code if we're not
careful we can just optimize for
coverage because coverage is useful but
it's not sufficient for a comprehensive
test Suite that's really insightful
response I remember you mentioned a
while ago that we want to have the
smallest possible test however I noticed
that the book also advocates for the use
of something that's called a test double
what is a test double and then at Google
what are the trade-offs that you face
when it comes to using these test
doubles so we talk about fakes and mocks
test doubles as as a kind of a class of
things here and often times we're
testing against complex systems so if
I'm testing against say a database I
want to test my software my software is
really the thing that's most important
to test not the database but I still
need to interact with the database to
exercise my software appropriately and
so a test double is a standin for a
complex system maybe it's a small
database that has specific data in it
than I can interact with directly maybe
it's a prescripted set of responses to a
server that is somewhere else and so
when I issue requests I get a specific
set of responses back
from the server it may live in memory in
the same process as the system being
tested so I don't have to worry about
Network effects or you know availability
of the remote server those kinds of
things are really useful for testing
they also add another complexity because
they aren't the real system so we're
getting farther away from the actual
production environment that our software
is going to live in and so if we're not
careful the double can not accurately
reflect the software as it will
eventually be run and that can cause
false confidence if we're not careful
the other problem is that they have to
exist and often times teams that create
expensive systems aren't the ones that
are running tests against them and so
they're not necessarily incentivized to
create the doubles and the other teams
would then use to run their tests
against and so there's an incentive
mismatch there that if we're not careful
can mean that other teams kind of build
test doubles in a Half Baked kind of way
and it's not really a sustainable way of
of using these across the ecosystem
you already know that Android and iOS
are operating systems designed to run
applications well algorand is also an
operating system just one designed to
run decentralized applications enabling
true peer-to-peer programmable value
exchanges Android and iOS operating
systems algorand decentralized operating
system blockchain doesn't sound so scary
now does it especially not scary you can
build on algor Brandon python the same
pure semantically normal python you
learned back in school and know fluently
no gimmicks try it today head to Alo
kit. that's ALG
kit. to set up your environment and get
coding in just 5
minutes you've given us a lot of really
interesting insights into some of the
low-level details related to testing at
Google I want to quickly take one step
back
we've talked about flaky tests or test
doubles and test coverage but earlier in
the show we talked about scale and
efficiency challenges can you comment a
little bit about the scale of testing at
Google so I can't give specific numbers
but I will say that we run a lot of
tests that it's possible with any
candidate change to test the transitive
closure of things that are dependent
upon that change so for example if I'm
making a change in a low library that
most of the Google infrastructure uses I
can run essentially all the tests at
Google against that low-level
infrastructure this can be expensive so
we have various techniques to do test
pooling test selection and you know
pruning the tree a little bit because in
some sense you know I really care about
the tests that are close to me in the
dependency graph and not the things that
are farthest away you know if one test
far away fails it's probably more likely
to be flaky then actually be a Bonafide
failure of my specific change and so
figuring out how to effectively run
tests in this way is an interesting
computational challenge you talked about
it being a challenge when it comes to
computation and I want to quickly turn
our attention to a discussion about
static analysis across the Google Cod
base because I expect that's a challenge
in a similar way before we get started
with that topic can you briefly comment
what is static analysis and how do you
use it at Google so static analysis is a
technique by where we can look at the
source code of a program and by
analyzing just the source code not
compiling and running the program but
just by analyzing the source code we can
learn things about the behavior of the
program this is contrasted with Dynamic
analysis which is running the program
oftentimes with instrumented libraries
and learning additional things about the
program we do both kinds of things but
we find that static analysis can
actually be really really powerful
so in light of the fact that static
analysis can be powerful and now you've
introduced that testing is a kind of
dynamic analysis can you briefly talk
about the tradeoffs or the benefits and
limitations of static and dynamic
analysis so sta analysis can't catch
everything obviously and that's okay
this is why we have many different sets
or many different steps of of
assurance but we want to catch as many
things as we possibly can inside of
static analysis because it's earlier in
the development cycle we don't actually
have to run the tests we can run this
stack analysis process over the code in
question there's a great story and I
don't remember if it made it into the
book or not but for a long time we've
had threading annotations available to
users within Google's codebase so you
can annotate a variable as I must hold a
specific lock as I access this variable
or I cannot call this function while I'm
holding this other lock and then static
analysis tooling will actually verify
that you are holding locks in a correct
way and will fail to compile the program
if you're not this is much better than
getting paged in the middle of the night
because you've got a deadlock somewhere
and your system just crashed there was a
team that was getting a bunch of
failures in their system and they
weren't common you know every couple of
weeks the system would crash they didn't
really understand why but they could
never track it down and then they had a
team fix it or they had a team
experience where they're going to we're
going to go add a bunch of these static
analysis annotations to our code base
and in doing so
their code failed to compile gee that's
weird I wonder why oh look there's a bug
here they fixed the bug and it fixed
this problem that they could never track
down on their own but now with the
additional Insight that stack analysis
gave them they were able to fix that bug
wow that's a really good example I
remember in the book it mentions a
static analysis tool called tricorder
what is tricorder and how do various
teams at Google use it for static
analysis purposes so tricorder and there
is an ixie paper about tricorder from
several years ago that folks can dig
into tricorder is a platform for doing
scalable static analysis and so
tricorder itself doesn't own the stack
analysis tooling but what it does is it
separates the consideration of scaling
and domain expertise so we have people
that work in Java or C++ or any number
of other languages that are really
experts in that language and they can
write stack analysis tools that say this
is a bug pattern a bug prone pattern you
shouldn't use this or this is an API
that we're trying to migrate away from
don't use that in fact use this other
thing instead and what tricorder does is
it takes all of those things and
collects them and then presents them at
an appropriate point in the development
cycle so it may present them in code
review if I'm writing a piece of code
and I accidentally write a bug and
there's an existing static analysis
check for that bug the code review tool
will tell me you have just written a bug
like click the button and we'll fix the
bug for you this also shows up if new
stack analysis checks are added we can
then see those in the existing Corpus of
code so the code index the code search
tool will show you as you're browsing
hey this is a place where your code can
be improved you know do you want to
create a change that makes that
Improvement and we even go so far as to
pull out existing findings and
automatically proactively send them to
teams as well so tricorder is kind of
the central part of managing that
process but there's a lot of other
pieces that go into making that
automated Improvement of source code
actually work so that sounds like an
awesome and super useful tool for
listeners who are interested in learning
more you mentioned ixie and that's the
International Conference on software
engineering I'm hoping that they'll go
there to check out that paper and we can
include it in the show notes as well I
want to turn our discussion to the next
topic because I know you're an expert on
the topic of large scale code changes so
very quickly what is a larg scale code
change and why do software engineers at
Google have to make these types of
changes so a large scale change or an
LSC as we've come to call them is a
change that you want to make to the code
base that is large enough that it's
impossible to do in an atomic change
right it may span tens of thousands of
files it could be something as simple as
I want to call a different function
right I'm deprecating some function and
I want to call some other function
instead or I'm deprecating this type
that people need to migrate to this
other type those changes it is not
technically possible nor desirable to
make that change across hundreds of
millions lines of code and one sweeping
move and so we have to figure out how do
we break that up into smaller chunks but
in LSC is generally done because we can
improve efficiency or we can improve
developer experience across the code
base we try to centrally manage those so
instead of every team having to make
this change we recognize there's a value
in having a central ized team make those
changes for everybody else so to be
clear is an LSC something that's done
manually is it done automatically or is
it some combination of automated and
manual approaches it kind of depends on
the nature of the change we want to
automate as much as we possibly can
sometimes it's as easy as writing an
appropriate you we were talking about
tricorder a minute ago writing an
appropriate stack analysis tool so that
people can automatically see what needs
to happen in their codebase click the
button and they get the fix themselves
there's certainly a lot of automated
tools that we can run across our code
base there's another paper from several
years ago called clang mrr that talks
about the way we automate changes across
our codebase by using the compiler and
tools that are built into the compiler
to make changes to our codebase so we
want to automate as much as possible
there are times when we can't automate
or there's certain circumstances in
which we can't automate and as a result
we've actually built and this is this is
an outg grow of the co era we actually
built a platform we call it busy beavers
for crowdsourcing a lot of those kinds
of things so sometimes there are tasks
that need to get done but still need a
human to look at and the Busy Beavers
platform allows anybody to enumerate a
set of tasks write some good
instructions post it on an internal
website and then anybody else can wander
by and just start picking tasks off that
list these tasks are designed to be
relatively easy to start Rel relatively
easy to finish but also easy to put down
if someone has to go work on something
else you can imagine this was very
useful during an era of Co shutdowns and
no one knowing what was going on but
it's utility has actually lasted a lot
longer than just that that sounds really
interesting so when you do a large scale
change through this busy beaver system
are you requesting changes to the
production code base or to CI
infrastructure or is it to test cases or
can it be all of those types of things
usually it's to the production code base
but it also may be test cases that are
need to be modified as well as part of
the production code base okay so once we
make these large scale changes my main
question is how do you know that the
large scale change was correct so I'll
go back to the more automated set
automated system example you if we need
to migrate something that exists in
10,000 files we can't test that I mean
we can test that using Google CI system
but it's actually really difficult if
the test fails to figure out which file
caused the fail
it's also difficult to get that
submitted to the codebase because merge
conflicts it's difficult to roll it back
if you need to roll it back for the same
reasons it's difficult to get it
approved by 10,000 different people and
so that is not really a feasible kind of
thing to do so what we do is we try to
design changes that can be split up into
many different parts so a 10,000 file
change may be split up into hundreds of
separate changes that are only 20 or 30
files a piece we can't can run those
through our continuous integration
system much easier we have a much better
signal as to whether that specific set
of files is correct or not and then we
can get them reviewed by someone who has
Global ownership over the entire
codebase and they can review them
individually using automated tools and
get those submitted to the codebase so
like how do we determine whether they're
correct or not using the same techniques
that we would use to determine whether
any other change is correct automated
testing and review okay you mentioned
before that the tricorder tool can
automatically suggest a change to the
code base if I'm a software engineer at
Google can I trust that the tricorder
change is going to be correct or does it
also have to go through code review and
automated testing so it also goes
through code review and automated
testing but this question of is this
correct is actually an interesting
cultural one early on when we were doing
a lot of these automated changes people
would push back how do I know that this
change is correct do I trust you there's
a strong culture of Ste ship within
Google's codebase everyone can read all
the source code but specific individuals
and teams are responsible for
maintaining specific parts of the
codebase and so the idea of an automated
system or even a centrally managed team
coming and making changes to my software
was a little bit foreign we had to build
a lot of trust by demonstrating that the
changes we were making were actually
beneficial and the feedback we've gotten
over the last several years as we've did
surveys and other kinds of discussion
amongst Engineers has has been that they
really appreciate this kind of automated
fixes and cleanup across their own code
bases thanks for that response if
listeners are interested in learning
more about testing we've had a number of
episodes on the topic on software
engineering radio so you may want to
check episode 595 or episode 572 which
we'll link to in the show notes ham
we've talked a lot about the various
approaches that Google takes in order to
create good software obviously creating
this book itself was a major endeavor
can you tell our listeners a little bit
about the process that you followed
simply to create the book in the first
place sure as I mentioned we knew we had
a message that we wanted to get out but
we weren't really sure how to do that
fortunately Tom manre who's one of the
other co-editors on the book has worked
in publishing before he was the
technical writer that oversaw and really
project managed the entire project and
he knew the process so that really
helped we went to O'Reilly we said this
is our plan this our thought are you
interested they said yes we were
and then we needed to find some content
we actually ended up crowdsourcing the
content within Google while Tom Titus
and I have a lot of expertise in many of
these areas again the genius myth we are
not the experts in all of them and so we
really wanted to get the experts on each
of those topics so each chapter is
written by the person that is on or runs
the team that is responsible for that
thing so it's really a great example of
people sharing their expertise in a way
we also wanted to make sure that each
chapter tied into the core themes of the
book you we talk about time tradeoffs
and scalability so we asked potential
chapter authors to provide just a short
thesis that demonstrated how their
proposed chapter would tie into those
themes at the end it was a lot of work
it was a ton of work it may have been
more work crowdsourcing the content than
it would have been if we all wrote it
ourselves but I feel like we got a
better product out of it I would also
say March of 2020 was not a good time to
release a book but I'm glad it's still
done well thank you for that response
Hyrum I appreciate it it sounds like you
applied many of the lessons about
software engineering at Google when you
were writing the book itself yes there
definitely was a certain amount of
self-referential experience as part of
that process so when you were writing
the book were there any I might call
them aha moments that you could share
with listeners so one thing you know I
mentioned those three themes time scale
and trade-offs there's another theme
that emerged as we reviewed content as
we talked to authors and that's one of
constraints and that's you know many of
us don't like constraints in our lives
we want to be able to do what we want to
do and do what we need to do that's not
feasible in an engineering organization
especially a large engineering
organization we can't let everyone
decide what compiler they want to use or
what you know operating system they're
going to run on or what programming
language they're going to use or how
they're going to use that programming
language because that eliminates a lot
of the benefits of the systems we have
in place to ensure scalability picking a
appropriate constraints as an
organization scales is actually a really
powerful way of enabling that kind of
scalability we kind of knew that going
in but it's amazing to me how that came
out in the book whether it's again large
scale changes or build systems or
testing infrastructure or style guides
all those things benefit from having
appropriate sets of constraints it's
possible to get them wrong I'd like to
think we've gotten a lot of them right
so it sounds like what you're saying is
that in many circumstances a constraint
can be positive even though initially we
might perceive it as being negative yes
we see that in our lives all the time
right a red light is a constraint in
some sense but I'm grateful it's there
so I don't get hit by somebody coming
the other direction and even in
engineering culture constraints are very
positive if we choose them correctly
again it's really easy to get them wrong
and I think a lot of times we do get
them wrong as a society as a engineering
culture but good constraints actually
add a lot of power to an organization
thanks for that response there's a lot
of content that we regrettably didn't
have time to cover because of time
constraints so I'm wondering is there
something specific in the book that we
didn't discuss that you'd like to
highlight now I briefly touched on those
three themes of time scale and
trade-offs the most important one of
those for me is time as we write
software as you write software think
about how long does this software have
to last am I just going to throw this
away tomorrow is it a bash script that's
going to exist on my command line or is
this something I need to have for the
next 10 years Google we actually think a
lot about this is software that's going
to last for a long time but that's not
always the case for everybody as you
think about how much time your software
has to last that informs a lot of the
other engineering decisions you make how
do I have to maintain this do I have to
be responsive to operating system
changes or programming language changes
or do I just have to hope that it lasts
until next week or if you're a student
until the programming assignment is due
but that's kind of one of those themes
that I think is really powerful but
doesn't show up in a lot of Industry
design discussions how long does the
software has to last can you give a
concrete example of how at Google you
make specific decisions for software
that has to live a long time sure I mean
we've talked a lot about maintainability
and the need to be able to maintain
software so we know that our existing
Corpus of software is going to have to
survive language changes Library updates
operating system changes all those kinds
of things that are ecosystem related
changes changes in the environment the
software runs under that's going to
happen at Google at software that runs
for a long time and so we have to think
about how are we going to update our
systems you know if the compiler updates
are we going to be able to fix all the
bugs that the new compiler may find that
the old compiler didn't find and how do
we do that using our processes or do we
need to invent new processes but those
really aren't problems that you have if
you're just trying to get something
shipped next week and and you don't have
to ever worry about it again you've
shared with us a number of
thought-provoking insights and I really
appreciate that in a way you've already
answered my next question but let's say
for example we have a junior software
engineer who's maybe studying the topic
or getting started in one of their first
jobs what kind of call to action would
you give to that individual so my advice
to them would be think Beyond just
programming again a junior person has
probably spent most of their University
time or most of their time focusing on
how to write code think Beyond just that
think where does my code fit in a
broader scheme of things why do these
processes exist it can often feel very
limiting I have to run tests I have to
write designs I have to participate in
meetings I just want to write code and I
get that I feel that way still sometimes
but those things are useful in terms of
solving the actual business problem if
you want to write code that's great but
it's a means to an end particularly if
you are employed somewhere right they're
paying you to solve a specific problem
so focus on the bigger picture and not
just I want to write this piece of code
today that's great advice now let's
imagine for a moment that our listener
is a well-established software engineer
what do you think that they should do to
level up their Knowledge and Skills
based on the content in the book I
mentioned earlier the book isn't
intended to be you should do the things
that we do so I want to be careful about
you know dictating especially to folks
that may have more experience than I do
what they should do I think the thing
that I would suggest is if you are
facing similar problems if you are
having difficulty scaling or if you're
working in an ecosystem that doesn't
have a good testing culture or a good
code review culture or some of those
other issues that we talked about in the
book think about how you can impact your
existing environment in a way that makes
those possible maybe you have to change
environments right that's always on the
table but think about you know can I
bring a better code review experience to
my employer if that's something that you
see is lacking our hope is that again we
don't tell you how to do these things
but we get you asking some of the
questions that maybe have difficulty
asking in the past wow that's a really
good point Hyrum thanks for sharing for
me one of the things that was beneficial
about the book was not only
understanding and learning about the
best practices at Google but doing
exactly what you just said which is
pausing to ask questions about what
might fit best for my own development
practices so thanks for the book a lot
as we draw our episode to a conclusion
I'm wondering if there's anything that
we've left out that you wanted to share
with listeners before we conclude I
think the one thing I would say is we
would appreciate your feedback the book
gets to available to open access on
abs. you can always buy a hard copy I
don't get any royalties from it so you
know I'm not saying that in a form of
self-promotion but you know if there are
areas in the book that you think that we
could improve or that should be
addressed in a separate way I don't know
that we're planning another addition but
we still want to hear about it so please
let us know all right thank you so much
for sharing if listeners are interested
in learning more about practices for
developing good software they may also
want to check out episode
430 hyam thank you so much for taking
time to chat with the listeners of
software engineering radio we really
appreciated this opportunity it's been
informative and educational if you are a
listener who wants to learn more I hope
you'll check the show notes for details
because we'll share all of the things
that hyam has mentioned those notes ham
thank you so much for being on the show
thanks a lot Greg it's been a lot of
fun thanks for listening to SC radio and
educational program brought to you by It
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-
radio.net this and all other episodes of
SE radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]